Jehovah God has the purpose
of gathering His people
エホバは目的を持って人々を—
サタンの世から
会衆へと集めてこられました
out of Satan’s world
into His congregation.
Christ Jesus promised us
that he would be with us
イエスも 事物の体制の終結の時まで
共にいると約束しておられます
until the conclusion
of this system of things.
この巨大な世界的組織を見る時—
When we see
this huge organization worldwide,
イエスがその約束を
守っておられること そして—
we know that Jesus
is fulfilling his promise
エホバが素晴らしい仕方で
ご自分の目的を—
and Jehovah is executing
His purposes in a wonderful way.
果たしておられることが分かります
This huge organization
has many services
この巨大な組織には
様々な奉仕の分野があります
or ministries
associated with it.
It can only be accomplished
by means of Jehovah.
このようなことができるのは
エホバだけです
He is the orchestrator
of this organization.
エホバがこの組織を
編成しておられます
The apostle Paul,
here in 1 Corinthians chapter 12,
使徒パウロは
コリント第一 12章で—
explains in great detail
エホバの組織の仕方について
詳しく述べています
how Jehovah
organizes His organization.
If we’d look at verse 14
of 1 Corinthians chapter 12,
12章14節にはこうあります
it says:
“Indeed, the body is made up
“実際 体は一つの肢体ではなく
多くの肢体です”
not of one member
but of many.”
So Paul is using the body,
the human body,
ここでパウロは 組織の類似として
人体を用いています
as an analogy
of the organization.
And it has many members.
人体には たくさんの部位があります
Each individual member
is assigned a ministry.
それぞれの部位には
それぞれの役割があります
Let us read here
verses 4 through 6.
12章4から6節を読みましょう
It says:
“Now there are different gifts,
“さて 賜物はさまざまですが
霊は同じです”
“but there is the same spirit;
“and there are different ministries,
“奉仕の務めはさまざまでも
主は同じです”
“and yet there is the same Lord;
“and there are different activities,
“働きはさまざまでも—”
“すべての人の中で
あらゆる働きをされる神は同じです”
“and yet it is the same God
who performs them all in everyone.”
This reminds us that this organization
does not belong to any man.
ですから この組織は
人間の組織ではありません
No human is putting it together;
人間が組織しているのでも
人間が動かしているのでもありません
no human is moving it along.
It is Jehovah God himself.
エホバがそうしておられるのです
And we are helped
by Paul in this chapter
同じ章でパウロは
わたしたち互いの関係について述べます
to understand
our relationship to one another.
17, 19, 21節を読みましょう
Let us read here
verses 17 and 19 and 21.
コリント第一 12章です
It says,
1 Corinthians 12:17:
17節 “もし全身が目であったなら
聴覚はどこなのですか”
“If the whole body were an eye,
“where would the sense of hearing be?
“それが聴くことばかりであったなら
においをかぐことはどこなのですか”
If it were all hearing,
where would the sense of smell be?”
19節—
Nineteen:
“If they were all the same member,
“もしそのすべてが一つの肢体であったなら
体はどこにあるのでしょうか”
where would the body be?”
And 21:
“The eye cannot say to the hand,
21節 “目は手に向かって「わたしに
あなたは必要でない」とは言えず—”
“‘I do not need you,’
“or again,
the head cannot say to the feet,
“頭も足に向かって「わたしにあなた方は
必要でない」とは言えません”
‘I do not need you.’”
We all understand
we need each other.
わたしたちは互いを必要としている
ということです
We do different operations
or ministries,
働きや任務はさまざまでも
互いを大いに必要としているのです
but we need each other
very much.
And that’s why it says
in verse 20:
それで 20節には “しかし今
それは多くの肢体であり—”
“Now they are many members,
yet one body.”
“それでもなお一つの体です”
とあります
We are still one body.
わたしたちは 一つの体—
We belong to the same congregation.
一つの会衆に属しているのです
Now, this brings us
to the text for today in verse 22
そして今日の聖句 22節です
where Paul says:
“On the contrary, the members of the body
“それどころか 実際には 体の中で—”
that seem to be weaker are necessary.”
“ほかより弱く見える肢体が
かえって必要なのであり” とあります
So “weaker” in this context,
what does it mean?
It does not refer
that this member is deficient
ここでいう “弱い” とは
どう意味でしょうか？
その “弱い” 人が
能力不足であるとか—
or not able
to do their work;
用をなさないという意味ではなく—
no, it just means
that this member may be,
from a physical point of view,
seem weaker.
身体的に弱く見えるということです
Maybe we have an older brother
病気に苦しむ年配の兄弟は
若いときほど働けないでしょう
suffering with some illness,
and he cannot do
as much as he used to do.
だからといって
割り当てを果たせないとか—
Does it mean that
he is not fulfilling his assignment
神の組織の中に居場所がないとか—
エホバにとって役立たず ということでは
決してありません
or that he does not fit
into God’s arrangement
or that he
is useless to Jehovah?
弱く見える人がいても
組織は機能します
Not at all.
He may seem to be weaker,
それが神の組織の素晴らしさです
but we understand
how that works,
and we appreciate
God’s arrangement.
23節にはこうあります
Look what it says in verse 23:
“また 体の中で
ほかより誉れが少ないと思える部分—”
“And the parts of the body
“that we think to be less honorable
“これをわたしたちは
より豊かな誉れをもって包みます”
“we surround with greater honor,
“こうしてわたしたちの
見栄えのしない部分に—”
“so our unseemly parts
“他より豊かな麗しさが
添えられ[ます]”
are treated with greater modesty.”
And this is God’s arrangement.
これが神の組織です
Verse 24 says:
24節 “一方 麗しい部分は
何も必要としません”
“Whereas our attractive parts
do not need anything.
“Nevertheless,
God has so composed the body,
“しかしそうではあっても
神が体を組み立てたのであり—”
giving greater honor
to the part that had a lack.”
“欠けたところのある部分に誉れを
より豊かに与えて[おられます]”
So there is no division
in the body.
ですから 体の各部は分裂することなく
協働しています
It cooperates.
You do not have members
looking down on others
他の部位が自分のように
動かないからと言って—
because of their inability
or limited circumstances.
見下げることはしません
25節にある通りです
That’s why it says in verse 25:
“So that there should be
no division in the body,
“体に分裂がないように—”
“その肢体が互いに対して
同じ気づかいを示すようにされました”
but its members should have
mutual concern for one another.”
How does this work?
エホバはこの組織をどのように
機能させておられるのでしょうか？
How has Jehovah arranged
and orchestrated this organization?
It’s beautifully described by Paul
エフェソス 4章16節のパウロの言葉に
美しく表現されています
in Ephesians 4:16.
まず15節には こうあります
Now in verse 15 here in Ephesians 4,
Paul says:
“すべての事において—”
“Let us by love grow up in all things
“頭であるキリストを目ざして
成長してゆきましょう”
into him who is the head, Christ.”
頭はキリストです
Christ Jesus is the Head.
ピラミッド型組織ではありません
There’s no pyramid structure.
“指導者は一人” と
キリストは言われました
Christ said:
“Your Leader is one.”
そして16節の前半で—
And then it says, from verse 16,
the first part of verse 16,
エホバの組織の仕方について
こう説明されています
it explains how Jehovah God
“このキリストをもととして
体の各部すべては—”
organizes his people.
“調和よく
組み合わされることにより—”
It says:
“From him,” from Christ,
“all the body
is harmoniously joined together
“また必要なものを与える
すべての関節を通して協働する”
“and made to cooperate
各部は調和し つながっています
through every joint
that gives what is needed.”
人の手のようです
So it is harmoniously joined together.
指は手のひらにつながり—
手のひらは手首につながっています
It’s like the human hand.
The fingers are joined by the palm.
調和よくつながり
ここで言われているように 協働します
The palm is joined to the wrist.
There is a harmonious joining together,
つながり 協力し 一緒に働くように
デザインされているのです
and then it says here,
they are made to cooperate.
エホバはそのように組織されました
So they have been designed
to fit together,
to cooperate,
to work together.
しかし わたしたちにも
行うべきことがあります
This is what Jehovah God does.
But then the second part of the verse
shows what we need to do.
16節は 必要とされているものを
与えるようにと述べてから こう続きます
It says we need to give what is needed
and then it says:
“それぞれの部分が定めの機能を
果たすにつれて—”
“When each respective member
functions properly,
“愛のうちに自らを築き上げることを
目ざした体の成長に資するのです”
“this contributes
to the growth of the body
as it builds itself up in love.”
ですから 与えること—
So that is our function
—to give what is needed,
求められることを行なうことが
わたしたちの役目なのです
to do what is required.
Jesus illustrated that
so beautifully for us in John 13.
イエスはそれを見事に実践されました
ヨハネ 13章の
弟子たちの足を洗った記録です
Remember the time when
he washed the feet of the disciples.
ヨハネ 13章12から15節を
お開きください
We turn there to John 13,
and if we look
ここでイエスは
ご自分がなさったことの意味と—
それを行なった理由を説明されます
at verses 12 through 15,
“さて 彼らの足を洗い
外衣を身に着け—”
Jesus explained what he did.
Then he explains the purpose of this.
“再び食卓について身を横にしてから
イエスは彼らに言われた”
It says:
“When, now, he had washed their feet
“and had put
his outer garments on,
“「わたしがあなた方にしたことが
分かりますか？”
“he again reclined at the table
and said to them:
“あなた方はわたしを
『師』また『主』と呼びます”
“‘Do you understand
what I have done to you?
“そう言うのは正しいことです
わたしはそのような者だからです”
“‘You address me
as “Teacher” and “Lord,”
“‘and you are correct,
for I am such.
“それで わたしが 主また師でありながら
あなた方の足を洗ったのであれば—”
“‘Therefore, if I, the Lord and Teacher,
washed your feet,
“‘you also should wash
the feet of one another.
“あなた方も互いに
足を洗い合うべきです”
“‘For I set the pattern for you,
“わたしはあなた方のために
模範を示しました”
that just as I did to you,
you should also do.’”
“あなた方も わたしがあなた方にしたと
同じようにするためです」”
So imagine, here is Jesus,
the Head of the congregation,
想像してみてください
he got down on his knees
会衆の頭イエスが 膝をついて
弟子の足を洗われたのです
and washed the feet of his disciples,
and then he said
そしてその手本に倣うようにと
おっしゃいました
we must follow that example.
So, what is the purpose
of this arrangement?
互いに仕え合う その目的は
何でしょうか？
Each of us fits
into God’s arrangement.
わたしたちすべてに
役割があります
All of us have a function,
a beautiful function,
それはとても美しい役割です
互いに仕え合い 必要とされているものを
与えるという役割です
that is to serve one another
—give what is needed.
As stated there in Ephesians
先ほど読んだエフェソス 4章16節の
最後にある通りです
in the final part of verse 16,
as we read:
“愛のうちに自らを築き上げることを
目ざした体の成長に資するのです”
“This contributes
to the growth of the body
as it builds itself up in love.”
So Jehovah has made
this wonderful arrangement
エホバがこのような仕方で
人々を組織されるのは—
実に素晴らしいことです
of gathering his people together.
He will take this organization,
this congregation of people,
エホバは
この組織 この会衆を—
義の行き渡る新しい世に
導き入れられます
through into
the righteous new system of things
そこでは
素晴らしい祝福が待っています
where we will experience
wonderful blessings.
しかし今でも
愛と一致を保ちながら協力し—
But right now,
it is our opportunity to cooperate
共に働くことができるのです
and to work together
in love and unity.
そうするなら 身体的に強いか弱いかに
かかわりなく—
And that way,
whether we are weaker or stronger
一つの体として
結び合わされていることになるでしょう
from a physical point of view
does not matter,
we’re all part of the same body.